So we're just going to head into public session,
for our last submission of this parliament
on the Conservation Amendment Bill.
And so our submission today is the Environmental Law Initiative, who are
joining us online.
Anna, we can see you there. Welcome to the select committee.
And Eliza, you have 15 minutes with us, so we'll hand it over to you, and then
we'll open up questions.
Kia ora. Tēnā koutou. Thank you for having us here, and acknowledging it's the
last moment to have our submission heard.
So we really appreciate having that opportunity today and squeezing that in amongst
the other business. So I'm Anna Simperning.
I'm here with Eliza Prestage-Oldfield.
We are both senior researchers at ELI, and we're here to present the ELI's oral
submission on the bill.
I'd say that ELI is more focused generally in its work on the implementation end of
environmental laws in New Zealand, the kind of space where
our laws are being applied by decision-makers or regulators,
and people with responsibilities under those laws to
apply them and give rise to the intention that those laws were set out to create.
So that's kind of the lens that we've come to the submission with.
We've looked at
what will this look like in that more implementation phase, where the rubber meets
the road. And on that, we've really honed in on the
changes to Clause 6 as a really core issue, and that's where we want to focus
today.
I just want to start by just reaffirming what a lot of submitters have
come to you with, which is how significant these changes are to our
conservation system in New Zealand.
It's probably fair to say that most New Zealanders have formative
experiences in our conservation estate and with our natural resources that are
really identity setting, and this Conservation Act is core to our national
identity. It's core to
who we are as New Zealand. It's part of our national heritage, and
it's how we look after our natural taonga.
So the changes here that have been proposed are significant in that context.
They have been framed in the explanatory statement, in the regulatory
impact assessments as more technical fixes, more about streamlining, creating
certainty. I just want to underline that ELI's submission is that that is not the
effect of the changes. They're not technical, and we don't agree that that is the
outcome of the changes, particularly with regard to Section 6E and
how the
Clause 6E and 6EA change that has been proposed.
That's primarily because that's part of the purpose architecture of
the bill, and the law, and it's that language that is coming
up in around economic opportunities and 6EA is also infused throughout the
system of the changes that have been proposed.
So they end up being really systemic.
And ELI's position is that if you're, as a committee, going to be looking at
addressing any kind of legitimate critique of that, you will be dealing with
systemic changes to the bill. So that's not really something that can easily be
glossed over with a technical fix or a small improvement to
the text. And I think that's also underlined with the way that the regulatory
impact assessment was carried out, it was very fragmented.
Looked at each part of the changes independently, and then came in right at the end
with looking at a purposive change to Section 6.
But in fact, that wasn't even the purposive change that we're seeing now coming
through in the
bill. So, procedurally, we find that
the proposal is
sort of undercooked. It's not been
conceived as a whole package, and so the impacts of that whole package haven't
really been properly thought through.
So I'll just come back to our core submission, which is that the bill should be
withdrawn. That is still ELI's position and submission following the committee's
interim report, which didn't touch on those Section 6EA
issues, and
the focus on the land exchange, and disposal provisions.
And the effect of that is ideally, while there are some
legitimate aspects of this bill that do need fixing and do need careful attention,
the effect of
reappraising the whole thing as a package through a comprehensive policy
development process would be that you can actually fix the bits that are broken
and need fixing, and you could then assess and model the impacts of those changes
on our conservation estate.
So
that's the sort of big picture. I'll just outline a taste of some of the issues
that we thought implementation-wise with Section 6EA will come up, and then I'll
pass on to Eliza, who's going to look in more detail at the potential
interaction with other legislation such as the Fisheries Act.
So you'll see in the submission we've outlined that some of the language used was
quite novel and undefined and unconstrained, would be open to interpretation by the
courts.
And the way that the Section
6EA used language that was already throughout Section 6 of the
Act could lead to internal conflicts that would need to be resolved.
And we also felt that internal-- yes, there could be internal conflicts in directly
applying the provisions, but also as Section 6EA is actioned, conflicts might
arise with other functions,
in relation to
broad scope of natural resources that is covered by that section.
Eliza, would you like to pick up on the fisheries
related issue?
Thanks, Anna.
And thank you to the committee for having us as your last submitter of
parliamentary year.
So the issues that my colleagues have already addressed, I think one aspect which
has sort of flown under the radar is there are some potential significant
unintended consequences here because the Conservation Act is the framework
legislation for the Department of Conservation.
It's not just about the management of the conservation estate, it's about all the
functions that DOC performs under any piece of legislation.
And so the changes to Section 6 through the new 6E , have potential
implications for other pieces of legislation which are, at the moment, working
quite well with DOC performing the conservation function and other actors
performing different functions.
A particular issue here is in the management of fisheries.
So, DOC's functions for marine reserves, has
functions under the Marine Mammals Protection Act, has functions under the Wildlife
Act. And there are other actors, like Maritime New Zealand under Maritime Transport
Act, and Fisheries New Zealand, who have functions under their own pieces of
legislation. And at the moment, they all work quite effectively together.
Um, Eli's brought some cases on this sort of examining the way in which DOC's
functions from conservation perspective are part of a package where fisheries is
looking at the economic, and sustainable use of fisheries, Maritime New Zealand is
looking at transport. If through Section 6E , DOC suddenly is
also focusing on economic opportunities to the greatest extent practical, which is
a very strong direction, that's going to leave no one functioning, focusing on the
conservation aspects. So if we're thinking about things like how you manage
interactions with marine bycatch, for example, how you manage protecting dolphins,
that's a really significant shift in New Zealand's law, and I don't think it was
intended or examined by the drafters.
So I see this as a legislative design issue, which is quite far reaching and quite
problematic.
There are also potential implications under the Reserves Act, which have a similar
sort of dynamic. So DOC, manages a whole of reserves.
They can be for all sorts of different purposes, including historical reserves.
Some cemeteries are managed by Department of Conservation.
And if you put that sort of economic opportunity gloss over a function like that,
it really doesn't work. Whereas the current statute with Section 6E, because of
framing that up so that any other use,
only if it's not inconsistent with conservation, that's a much clearer delineation
of the different purposes of different agencies and the sort of hierarchy of uses
where you say, "Absolutely you can pursue tourism, recreation, but conservation
comes first." And I think that's what most people sort of think sort of should be
the case for a department named Department of Conservation.
So I think this is something that the Select Committee really needs to turn their
attention to. It's much broader than just how do we facilitate additional economic
opportunities on conservation land.
It's potentially sort of undermining the whole purpose of a separate Department of
Conservation, and creating some major downstream consequences for our
protected species, for reserve areas.
Yeah. We only have a few more minutes, and we haven't had any questions yet, so
I'll wrap up there and hand back over to the committee to ask us any follow-ups.
Yeah. Brilliant. Thank you very much for that submission.
Yes, we've got a couple of minutes for questions.
We'll go first to Rachel Brooking.
Thank you. Thank you for an excellent submission and your point about it being
framework legislation. I think a whole lot of past conservation ministers have just
written to the Minister about that very point, and it's well made.
Thank you for that. But also on this whole package issue that you were talking
about, which is different from the relationship to other legislation.
But throughout the bill, the economics is referred to.
Do you want to just tell us if you think there could be a fix for it?
So Labor has consistently said that we would get rid of 6E .
So if you got rid of that, then I think the point of your submission is you'd have
to get, change a whole lot of text throughout the bill.
If you could do that, would you still be opposed to the bill?
Hmm, good question.
I think a
key point with-- I think that would be obviously preferable to what we have now.
So,
that would be something we'd support on that basis, but not our preference.
I think the point is that
the analysis just hasn't been done for us to inform what the impact of
the changes to the 6E component could
have throughout the rest. So it would depend on the exact wording of whatever was
proposed.
The change to Section 6E as it stands without Section 6E is much closer to
the original wording, but it's not exactly there, and presumably there would need
to be some kind of integration with the other aspects that 6E is intended to cover.
So I think if that was to happen, again, analysis would need to be done
on how that
flows through every layer of the framework and then how those
changes are made and the other provisions that replicate that language.
And I think given that that kind of framework look at the system hasn't
really occurred, like all of the different components have been
investigated separately or there is a gap there that needs to be filled,
and that's why we think it does need to be withdrawn and does all need to be looked
at as a complete package.
Yeah. Thank you.
Thank you. And Priyanka.
Yeah. So that was one of my questions, so I'll ask my other one.
And echoing what Rachel said about a really good submission, so thank you.
Your point around the treaty obligation changes, you've made the point that Section
4-- Section 4A establishes a new code and kind of supersedes Section 4 that's in
there. Do you see any need for there to be an additional interpretation section
there at all, or do you just think it should be left with Section 4?
Hmm. So are you suggesting whether there should be a further different change to
the current position?
Or just take out 4A.
Take out.
Yeah. Eliza, do you have
feedback on that? I- Um, I mean, there had been work done under a previous minister
on Te Tiriti partnership more generally in conservation.
I think it is an area that still needs further consideration.
But I don't think an alternative provision would be wise at the current point in
time when that underlying work wasn't really completed.
So I think making sure that there's a clear treaty clause is important.
And then in terms of more kind of itemized obligations, I think that work still
needs to be ongoing and
consider the alignment with treaty settlements and with the role of
conservation boards.
I know there are some iwi who are sort of looking at the more recent settlements of
having the Tangata Whenua settlement, for example, and thinking, "Oh, it'd be
really cool to see if we can get something a bit like that in our waka." But I
think that's a much, much bigger question, and probably better not to sort of have
a short-term patch on it in this legislation, but better to allow that work to
continue.
So delete.
Yeah. Uh, thanks. Thank you. Look, one last question, Lan.
Tina Koroa, thank you so much for a great submission.
My question was just asking you to expand on the point you made.
Like you mentioned, the Marine Mammals, uh, Act and the Marine Reserves Act, and
how like no one would be fulfilling that conservation purpose.
Can you just explain that in very basic terms for us here at the committee?
Yeah, happy to. Kia ora, Lan. So Eli has brought a case which has recently
been in the Court of Appeal around marine bycatch, and it provides a really solid
example of this issue. Under the Wildlife Act, the Department of Conservation, um,
has quite strong powers to create plans to protect
endangered wildlife. There are similar provisions under the Marine Mammals Act, and
the Marine Protection Act is its own statute.
So all of those pieces of legislation have a really strong protective function for
the Department of Conservation to try and minimize risks to endangered wildlife.
Whether those are risks from fisheries or whether there are other risks, disease,
DOC is meant to be doing protective actions.
That stock's only mandate. DOC isn't balancing those protective actions with
anything else. Any countervailing considerations come in somewhere else in the
system. So if, for example, there's an intervention which might be great for the
dolphins but might reduce the total allowable catch, Fisheries
New Zealand takes the-- They're the ones who are looking at what's the impact of
this on fisheries, and DOC is looking at what's the impact of this on dolphins.
I think the way this change is framed, it's going to make it very difficult for DOC
to be clear in its own mandate and focus on those conservation aspects.
So it's effectively tipping the balance by requiring DOC to already balance
in considerations that they currently shouldn't, they currently don't need to, and
that within the sort of structure of legislation across the different pieces of the
framework, it's going to be death by 1,000 cuts if DOC is
already sort of saying, "Oh, we probably shouldn't do that because, yeah, it's good
for the dolphins, but..." And it's much, much better to have separate functions in
the system so that they can all be sort of considered on their own merits.
Thank you. That's really helpful.
Look, thank you very much, uh, for your submission today.
Uh, in the final select committee of the 54th Parliament, this has been
the last submission that has been heard by this Parliament.
But hearings of submissions can continue through to the 55th Parliament, and
consideration of this bill will continue.
So thank you to submitters that we have heard so far. Thank you to you.
We do really value that feedback that we've received.
As officials obviously will also be working throughout the next couple of months,
to provide feedback and advice as to what we've heard from submissions as well.
So really, really helpful. So thank you very much.
Just this committee.
Just this committee. Yes. So thank you.
Since I helped you. Bye. Thank you.
Thanks very much. Thank you. Bye